Okay, we have got a real treat for you today.
We have an interview with the person who I believe
is the most important economist in the world today.
I'm not just saying that, I really believe it.
This guy is the world leader
in inequality, in the taxation of the super-rich.
I really think this
guy is the guy to show to the Labour Party,
or whoever is in charge in your country,
that wealth taxes are not just some radical
out of their idea for, like, lefty tree-hugging hippies.
Academics believe in this.
The work is being done.
The design work is being done on how...
Specifically how to tax the rich.
I really want to show him to,
you know, the political class,
people like Rory Stewart on The Rest is Politics,
who has been asking, "Where are the academics?
Where are the professors?" If you want to see
the academics, the professors, this is the guy.
So Rory Stewart, get him on your show.
You're going to get on with him like a house on fire.
This is the guy we're missing, I think.
The guy who really does the work.
He's just had his recent book
translated into English.
It's called We Need to Tax Billionaires.
It's a short book,
it's not expensive and it's quick to read,
and it's the missing link in my opinion.
The actual how do we do it,
the specifics on how do we do it.
So excited to introduce you
to the most important economist
in the world, Gabriel Zucman.
Okay.
Welcome, Gabriel Zucman, to the United Kingdom.
Thank you very much for coming,
for visiting my wonderful kitchen.
Thanks for having me.
Thanks for all of your work across the years
on inequality on wealth taxes, and thanks for
writing this book, getting it translated into English.
do you have...
I don't know if you have this phrase in France.
We have it in English.
You wait ages for a bus, and then 2 come along at once.
Do you have a similar phrase in French?
No?
No, not really.
Well,
I feel a little bit like this meeting you,
because the first time we met was 2 weeks ago,
in Paris.
when I went there
for the promotion of the French translation of my book.
Now we're meeting again for the first time in the UK.
But do you remember...
You probably don't remember.
Do you remember roughly when the first time
I ever got in touch with you via email was?
Perhaps 5, 6 years ago.
I looked it up before this interview.
It was the 22nd of May, 2015.
So exactly 11 years ago.
And I read it.
It was a kind of embarrassing,
embarrassingly long email.
You were probably too busy to read it,
but you very kindly replied.
And then over the 11 years since then,
a number of times I've reached out to you for help,
for advice.
Where should I go to university?
How should I study economics?
And you replied every time.
So thank you very much
for all of your help across the years.
And I've been following your work very,
very closely, and you're obviously very well known
in France now, the work you're doing now.
But obviously we're in England now-
And a lot of our viewers
maybe won't know who you are.
So could you tell us a little bit
about who you are and what you do?
I'm Gabriel Zucman.
I'm a professor of economics,
at the Paris School of Economics
and the University of California in Berkeley,
and I'm also the director
of the International Tax Observatory.
We do research on inequality and taxation,
with a focus on the super-rich,
multinational companies, tax avoidance, and how we
can fix those problems.
These are some of the most pressing issues of our time.
Especially the explosion of billionaire wealth-
Has been one of the most dramatic evolution
of the world economy of the last decades.
It started in 1980s.
It accelerated after the financial crisis of 2008, 2009.
And now there's an acceleration of the acceleration-
Over the last couple of years.
If you look at the wealth of global billionaires,
it has increased by 40% in just 2 years,
coming on top of everything that had happened before,
and with the explosion of their wealth,
there's an explosion of their influence.
There's an explosion of their power.
And we are seeing it everywhere.
And a lot,
frankly, of what's happening in our democracies
Is downstream of this explosion
of billionaire influence.
And so it's, frankly, it's difficult to
study anything else than that at the moment.
I really think
it's the main economic and political issue of our time.
Hence, a lot of our work these days is about that.
Well, people who watch this channel
will know I couldn't agree more.
Obviously, it's something I'm very passionate about.
I'm quite interested in understanding...
So I studied economics.
I went to London School of Economics.
We're about similar age,
so I went there 2005 to 2008.
Then more recently,
I went to Oxford and did a master's.
I'm interested in how you ended up studying economics
and also studying inequality
because from my experience of economics,
actually,
at universities,
there's not a lot of discussion of inequality.
Would you be able to tell us a little bit about
where you're from, what was like... what was life like
growing up, and how you ended up studying economics?
Well, I grew up in Paris.
I did my studies in France.
And then I got a job in the US,
and so I moved to the US and I lived in,
Berkeley in the San Francisco Bay Area for about
10 years.
Okay.
How old were you when you were living in San Francisco?
I moved when I was 26.
And it, you know, it kind of radicalised me
because in the San Francisco Bay Area,
You have the wealthiest people in the world.
You have the tech billionaires living nearby,
close to thousands, tens of thousands
of homeless people in San Francisco,
Berkeley, everywhere.
So tremendous, gigantic inequality, you know?
And I was also there when,
Trump got elected in 2016,
And I witnessed first,
firsthand,
like,
the failure of the Democratic Party
to address the phenomenal increase in inequality
in the US, to propose concrete,
practical, and ambitious solutions to that problem.
And so it led me first to kind of study,
inequality, especially in the US,
but also from a global perspective,
spend all my time
and energy doing that, but also progressively to try
to think about, okay, how should we fight it?
Yeah.
It's good, it's important to study.
And, it all starts with that.
Creating clarity, transparency, making objective
the situation that exists today.
It's already starting to change,
things a little bit.
But then more recently I kind of tried
to do more actionable policy work.
So hence the book,
How we should tax...
Why we need to tax billionaires,
of course, but more importantly,
what can we learn from the historical experience,
from the international experience?
Yeah.
And the lessons we can draw to effectively,
tax the billionaires today
in a way that would really work.
I'm really interested
in this move you've made from academia into,
like, basically actively trying to fight inequality,
because it's not an easy move to make.
I want to talk a little bit about that,
but before I get onto that,
I just want to know a little bit
about what it was like for you within academia
working on and trying to work on inequality because...
So I did a masters at Oxford 2017 to 2019.
And I went there
with basically the intention of working on inequality.
They had one guy there who worked on inequality.
I think it was Tony Atkinson.
He died before I went there.
He was about, like, 85 or something.
And then there was nobody
in the entire Oxford economics department
working on inequality.
I tried my best
to choose subjects that were about inequality.
I couldn't find a single one.
I wrote my thesis about inequality.
I couldn't find a supervisor.
I had to go outside of the department.
And when I was there, the general consensus was,
you will not be able to succeed as an academic
in academic economics
if you choose inequality as your focus.
So that was my experience.
But, you are, I'm aware, have been in academia
much longer than me.
Have things changed?
Did you experience anything like that?
How do you think academic economics is now
with regards
to being able to seriously look at inequality?
Yeah, and I think what you describe is spot on.
I do think there is also some progress.
Maybe because.. look, for a period of time,
let's say,
after World War II, from the post-war years until
the fall of the Berlin Wall,
all of economics was essentially about just efficiency.
The debate of the time was really
about whether the market economy or the planned economy
is the most efficient.
And,
inequality,
distributional questions,
nobody cared about those issues at the time.
But it was a kind of parenthesis
because economics originally, if you look at economics
as it was practiced in the 19th century,
if you look at the kind of the classical economies
of the time, whether it's Malthus, Ricardo Marx,
Smith, they were all very much interested
in distributional questions.
What mattered for them was to understand
the tenden... the long-run tendencies and how income
is distributed between landowners, workers, and so on.
And so that's how economics used to be.
There was this parenthesis during the Cold War.
And after the end of the Cold War,
inequality started very gradually,
and it's been way too slow, but to make a comeback
at the center of the economics discipline.
And you mentioned Tony Atkinson,
who played an incredibly important role in all of that,
who was one of the first...
British economist at
British economist who was professor at Oxford
and who was instrumental in reviving the study...
I've got his book over there.
You can probably...
In the shelf,
Yeah, Inequality.
Next to that,
his-
His last, book, exactly.
Yes.
Very important and really instrumental in reviving
the study of the long-run trends in income
and wealth concentration.
And he's been an inspirational figure for me.
I've known him in,
when I was doing my PhD in Paris.
I met with him numerous times.
And more broadly,
he was continuing a tradition that I feel
very much a part of with... which is this tradition
of empirical social sciences.
Which is data-based.
Yeah, exactly.
Which was so strong
in England, in the UK for a long time.
Like, the inventors, for instance,
of the national accounts,
which are the GDP statistics,
the way we quantify economic activity.
These are the... these
are British economists of the 17th century.
Gregory King, William Petty.
And they were interested
not only in measuring the economy as a whole,
but also in inequality,
The first attempt at measuring national income,
by the famous social table of,
Gregory King, he tries to estimate the total income
of England, but also the income of each social class.
Like,
you know,
the kings,
the baronets,
The workers, and so on and so on.
And there is this long tradition that started
in the 17th century that has continued over time.
Tony Atkinson was,
a great part of this tradition
that I'm trying at a very modest level to continue
myself with a focus on
international economic relations.
That's what mostly I'm interested in.
And, you know, billionaires, to be honest,
it's not my passion.
I think it's, as I said,
very important
to study them given
everything that's happening.
But deep down, most of my work has been more about,
the organisation of international economic relations.
How this changes over time.
And the dynamics of coordination
or competition across countries,
the consequences this has for inequality.
And so on.
So just very quickly,
because I want to get onto your political work,
we often get messaged by young people
who want to study economics,
and they want to study inequality specifically.
That's something I struggled with.
Just very quickly, what advice would you have for
maybe young people here in the UK or in other countries
that are thinking about studying economics at university
and want to focus on inequality?
I found that difficult.
Have you got
any advice for how people can go about doing that,
where they should study, what they should do?
Yeah, I mean, do it.
And be the change you want to see.
That's my advice.
And we need more people
studying
inequality within academia.
And, you know, there's been some progress
thanks to people like Tony Atkinson,
but the movement needs to
grow, and so it's on all of us
to contribute to that.
And I think this is the direction that we're taking.
It's too slow,
but this is where we're going as a discipline.
Well, just for me personally,
the work that, you yourself have done
and the work that Thomas Piketty has done was,
Thomas Piketty,
another very well-known French economist,
who you've worked a lot with.
It really inspired me.
I think Thomas Piketty's big book,
Capital, came out, I think, in 2012, when I was still
working as a trader for Citibank.
And that's what is in the bookshelf
next to Atkinson's Inequality book in that nice cover.
And before I read that book, I didn't know that
any economists were seriously looking at inequality.
So, the work that he's done and the work that,
that you've done and Emmanuel Saez, a group of
French economists was really inspirational for me.
So thank you for that,
and send my thanks to Piketty.
I know you speak to him a lot.
But I want to get onto your political work,
because you've made this big shift,
which to me is super interesting
because I don't see many...
I mean, in a sense, it's a shift that I've made as well,
but I don't see many people
who are sort of top-level academics who've decided,
"You know what?" And correct me if you don't think
this is a correct description of what you've been doing,
but it seems to me like you've really decided,
"I'm going to really shift my focus into not just,
writing papers and getting
prestigious positions on this, I want to try and
to do something about..." You know, your book is called
We Need to Tax Billionaires, which is quite political.
Why did you decide,
"I'm going to..."
you have a very good record in economics.
You're a professor
at a couple of very good universities.
You could very easily have just written
a couple of, op-eds in newspapers
and had a few rounds of applause.
But from what I've seen of your work,
you've got a big presence on social media.
You're making videos on Instagram.
You've got something like 300,000 followers
on Instagram.
Correct me if I'm wrong,
I suspect that's maybe not what you imagined
your life going in that direction a number of years ago.
Why did you make this big shift into, like...
And also, you have become very well known
in France, that the form of taxation on the
super-rich which is popular in France is known
as the Zucman tax, which is your name, your face.
I would guess you've sacrificed
a lot of, your privacy for this.
What made you decide
to take this hard turn and really try
to become aggressively politically active?
Well, for me, it's part of the job of
being a researcher in the social sciences.
Meaning, there are different intellectual traditions,
right, in the social sciences, but the tradition
I feel closest to is the tradition in which
the reason why we study society is not just because
it exists, like stars in the sky,
but it's to contribute at a very modest level
to improving policies and to improving societies.
Yeah.
And so it all starts with a kind of research and
establishing facts and understanding the problems.
But to me, it seems that once you've understood
those problems, when you've established facts,
once you've created
knowledge, it's part of the job, first of all,
to contribute to disseminating that knowledge,
in the broader population.
Of course, it would be much more comfortable,
for me to just,
stay in the ivory tower
and just have seminars with my peers
and, a small group of experts.
But once you've found facts
about the magnitude of tax evasion.
Yeah
...
About the effective tax rates
of the different groups of the population.
How much the rich pay in tax
relative to the middle class, these are some of the most
important elements of information for our democracy.
And so for me, first of all, it's part of the job
to make sure that everybody knows about those facts,
that this knowledge belongs to society and not just
to a tiny group of experts, number one.
Number 2, for me, it's also part of the job
to propose solutions when problems have been found.
And today, there is a major anomaly in our societies,
which is that the super-rich pay much less tax,
relative to their income
than the rest of the population,
and we'll come back to that.
But once you've found problems, I think it's part
of the job to say, "Okay, look, how can we fix that?"
Yeah.
Not with a technocratic approach,
which I very much dislike,
which would be like, "The experts have demonstrated
that you need to do X, and if you disagree with that
it means you're a populist" or whatever.
No, not at all.
But to offer solutions to feed a,
a vibrant public conversation, a public debate.
It's for people, it's for citizens to decide
through democratic deliberation and the vote.
But where researchers like myself can contribute
is by saying, "Okay, there is this problem,
and here is a potential solution."
Now, we can have a...
There are always trade-offs, pros and cons.
We can discuss that,
but here is one way to do things.
Maybe we didn't... we might have not thought of it
exactly in those terms before,
but here's a potential solution.
And of course, if you propose solutions,
I think it's also part of the job to try to defend
those proposals.
Because, it's not enough to say,
"Well, I think we can tax billionaires like that."
Yeah.
And then, you know, to log off
and not answer any questions.
No, no, no.
I think it's also part of the job to explain,
"Well,
okay, sure, there are potential questions
and problems, but here are the answers."
And so for me, it's really a natural part of the job,
of what it means to be
a researcher
in the social sciences.
Not everybody in the field agrees with that view.
Some people think that, they should not
be involved in public conversation, and this should be 2
separate spheres.
But that's no... that's not how I view,
how I view all of that.
Has it been difficult for you personally?
People watching from outside France might not be aware
that you are like really quite well known in France,
and that, I guess, that's happened quite quickly.
Like has it...
As you...
I don't know.
I suppose you're quite a private person naturally.
Yes.
Has it been difficult, this like sudden transition into,
to being quite well known
in a country where you live, where you're from?
Well,
there are, positive and less
positive aspects to that.
So let's say,
So it's true that, for my sins,
this tax proposal has come-
Be known as the Zucman Tax.
Which was not,
something-
Not your idea.
No, not my idea.
Clearly not.
Okay.
What's the positive side to it?
The positive side is that,
it forces everybody
to try to understand what this is about.
It's a new proposal.
It's a new idea.
It's not just...
For instance, France used to have a wealth tax for a
very long time,
and it's not recreating the wealth tax.
Yeah.
It's something else.
So it has a new name,
so everybody has to try to make an effort.
Sometimes the opponents of the measure
didn't make that effort to try to
understand what this is about.
The difference is that the Zucman Tax is attem-
Correct me if I'm wrong, is attempting to be
really tightly focused on making sure
it is really the very rich, the richest people pay it,
the richest people don't avoid
Is that correct?
Yes, so there are different elements.
So first of all,
it's most importantly, it's about creating
a new principle.
The principle is that if you are extremely wealthy,
and we can debate what it means, but I've proposed
earning more than $100 million in wealth.
If you're extremely wealthy,
you have to pay an unavoidable minimum amount
of tax each
and every year.
Okay, so it's trivial.
You might say, "Well, surely this must be already
somewhere in our laws."
Except it's not.
Yeah.
So we need to create this principle
that, you can't pay 0.
And today some of those billionaires, they pay 0.
You had revelations a few years ago by the US
media, ProPublica, on the taxes paid by US billionaires.
And you saw people like Elon Musk, Jeff Bezos-
Paying 0 tax
Paying 0 tax.
There's even one year,
Jeff Bezos receives a check,
A tax credit,
for children.
So that's just wrong.
Yeah.
Everybody agrees with that.
So there has to be a floor.
First of all,
the floor.
So that everybody understands
the proposal, there has to be a minimum.
Now-
And this is on the basis that
the moment, these people are paying less
in percentage terms than cleaners, and taxi drivers,
and hairdressers, and teachers.
Yeah.
So there has to be a minimum.
Then for the minimum to be effective
it has to be expressed not as a fraction of income,
because the whole problem is that those billionaires-
Because they have no income tax,
They manage to report no income, like Jeff Bezos.
Yeah.
Right?
In a technical sense
Of course, in a real sense they have income,
but-
From the perspective of the tax law,
they manage to pretend that they income.
They're redefining their income as-
Like as,
as CEO of Amazon, Jeff Bezos didn't pay himself a wage.
As controlling shareholder of Amazon,
he instructed the company not to distribute dividends.
He didn't sell shares,
and so he didn't realise capital gains.
And so his taxable income was truly 0.
But of course his-
No tax evasion here.
His company's making enormous profits,
but none of them,
and he owns the company.
And he owns the company.
Essentially, all the money stays in this bucket.
None of it comes to this bucket,
so officially I have no income.
Exactly.
So his true economic income-
Is enormous
Is very large.
It's in the billions.
His wealth is gigantic, but he paid no income tax,
and that's legal, and that's the way
the system works, but of course it's not a good way.
It's not a good system.
So we need to create a minimum.
For the minimum to be effective, it has to be expressed
not as a fraction of taxable income,
but as a fraction of wealth.
Which is much harder
Because that's the only way to make it,
to make it unavoidable
To manipulate
Because they can technically reduce their income to 0,
but of course
they cannot reduce technically their wealth to 0.
Exactly.
Yeah.
That's the basic idea.
So minimum expressed as a fraction of wealth.
Then if you choose a rate of 2% on wealth,
not a higher rate, it's the rate that would ensure that
the billionaires would pay as much tax,
all tax included,
relative to their income,
than the rest of the population.
That's how the rate was computed.
So basically it all starts from all the,
body of work, international research effort
that was done over the last five,
six years that has established that the billionaires,
the super-rich, have much lower effective tax rates.
All tax included, than the rest of the population.
Especially, in particular, and that's the main reason,
because of the failure of the income tax
to effectively tax them.
Okay, so if you want to correct this anomaly,
you need something,
a minimum tax that's based on wealth.
And so that's the problem.
And with 2%, you know, it's really low, 2%.
There are many reasons why you might want
to have higher tax rates than that on the super-rich.
Personally, I would favour much higher rates than that.
Let's be clear.
I worked with Bernie Sanders, for instance, in the US
when he was running for president, and his tax program,
he was proposing rates of up to 8% on wealth
for people with more than $10 billion in wealth.
All of that makes a lot of sense.
But my thinking here was, okay, how can we,
design something that everybody should agree on?
It's just not possible
to defend the notion that billionaires should be allowed
to pay less tax than the rest of the population.
It's just a blatant violation
of our most basic principles of equality before the law,
which are at the core of our democracies.
So we should all be able to agree at least on that.
And that was the proposal.
Yeah.
And originally it was,
formulated
in 2024,
when Brazil had the presidency of the G20,
and they wanted to put on the agenda of the G20
some new ideas
for international cooperation.
And in 2021,
there had been a minimum tax on multinational companies
that had been agreed on by 130 countries.
And so I thought,
well,
okay, let's try to do for billionaires
what we've been able to do in a very limited manner,
but still it exists,
for multinational companies.
So the idea of a minimum tax, let's do it.
Let's try to do it for billionaires.
And then the Brazilian government said, "Let's do it.
Great idea."
And so they kind of,
they put it on the agenda of the G20.
These G20 finance ministers,
they meet several times a year.
Not once,
Since the creation of the G20 25 years ago,
not once had they discussed those questions of
taxation of the very rich.
The boom in extreme wealth, which are some
of the most important, frankly, issues of our time.
And so the... the fact that for the first time
they were forced to talk about that,
it kind of kickstarted a conversation
in different countries.
So that's why then the French National Assembly
picked up that proposal.
Like, exactly what the...
what I had formulated in my report to the G20 in
June 2024 was then translated into a bill
that was passed by the French National Assembly
in February of 2025, minimum tax of 2% of wealth
for people with more than 100 million euros.
Yeah.
And it was passed-
Yes,
in France
It passed, it passed National Assembly,
which is, it's not a left-wing parliament.
Yeah.
Far from it.
And yet it passed.
And then, okay, it was blocked by the Senate.
And so it's still not enacted into law, but it's going
to come back and eventually, I'm very confident
that it will end up passing because
it's the current situation which is just radical,
and unacceptable.
You think you will get it in France?
You think you will get the wealth tax through?
Well, I'm pretty certain that it will happen
in France, and more than that, I think it will-
Roughly long do you think it will take?
It will happen in other countries,
and eventually
it will be,
I think the most likely scenario is that
it will become, it will happen a bit like
the creation of the progressive income tax happened
at the beginning of the 20th century.
So it was an international movement.
You know,
for centuries,
The way that we did taxation was extremely unfair.
It was, taxes were only based on consumption.
Things like salt,
and commodities, and so it was a heavy burden
for the poor.
Regular people.
And the rich didn't have to pay taxes etc.
And so then there is this revolution,
beginning of 20th centuries where different countries
said, "No, no, look, we are going
to have a progressive income tax
with higher rates for higher incomes."
The UK actually was a leader,
because it happened in 1909
with the famous People's Budget
of Lloyd George, where in 1909 Lloyd George says,
"Okay,
we are going to introduce a progressive income tax."
And there was already an income tax in the UK,
but at a flat rate, same rate for
everybody since 1843.
And in 1909, People's Budget, there's a 2.5% super tax
on top of the regular income tax that's introduced
for the 10,000 wealthiest people in the UK.
And that's the birth of the progressive income tax.
France did the same in 1914.
The US did the same in 1913.
Many countries kind of did it at roughly the same time.
It was not an international agreement,
but it was just a common realisation that,
we need more money for pen- for workers' pensions.
For many things,
and the way we do things at the moment is really unfair.
Yeah.
And so we need to make sure
that the rich pay their fair share.
And so,
and then the income tax became much more progressive,
over the course of the 20th century.
And my feeling is that something a bit like that-
Will happen
Will happen.
And it's starting to hap- to happen.
Yeah.
Are you familiar much with the conversation in,
in this country about wealth taxes?
Yes.
Because I'd like to speak about it a little bit.
I think when you say that,
you see the wealth tax as similar to the income tax,
I think that's, for me, that's super interesting.
When I was writing my book,
I was reading Hard Times by Charles Dickens.
And they're talking at the time
about taxing the factory owners.
And the factory owners say, "Oh, it's impossible.
If you tax us, we'll throw the factories into the sea."
So I think if you look at history,
like, it shows,
of course, rich people are going to fight against this.
And rich people in this country
are fighting against this.
That's good.
I was discussed...
What, do know what The Rest Is Politics is?
Yes.
It's the biggest politics show in,
politics... podcast in this country.
I've been telling them aggressively
that if they're serious on the economy,
they should have you on, and they definitely should.
But they mentioned me in their show last night.
And they said, "People like Gary Stevenson just
want to take money from the rich and give it to the poor."
What do you think about that argument?
I think first of all,
what's truly radical
is the current situation, where the super-rich can live
in their own parallel society
tax-free, even though their wealth is a social creation,
is a collective success.
You don't become
a billionaire by your own, right?
You've benefited from education,
from healthcare, from all the public infrastructure
that has made it possible for your businesses to thrive,
the locals that protect your properties,
and so on and so on.
And so,
it's wealth creation is
always a social creation.
They benefit from subsidies oftentimes.
And the notion that you can become extremely rich
thanks to the collaboration of millions of people
and then have no duty whatsoever towards society
is just, you know, totally radical.
So that's the current situation.
And that's what we need to fix.
And let me just emphasise that
even though we could suspect
that the super-rich were not paying their fair share,
and you had,
revelations,
I mentioned, ProPublica in the US,
until recently, there was just no hard data.
And a lot of the work-
You've been doing a lot of work collecting-
We've done the work.
So you are convinced inequality is increasing?
And it's not,
and it's not easy work because there's
a tremendous,
tremendous opacity
about the super-rich.
There's no public official statistics
about their wealth,
about their income, about the taxes that they pay,
and it's only by working in partnership
with tax administrations in different
countries that we are able to establish the facts.
We have about 10 countries now
where we see everywhere that... the same pattern.
Whether it's France,
whether it's the Netherlands, Italy, Brazil,
Norway, Sweden.
Everywhere.
The working class, the middle class pays a lot of tax.
Rough...
All taxes included, roughly 40, 50% of their income,
in VAT, in payroll taxes,
in property taxes, income tax, all included.
40, 50%.
And then the billionaires,
they pay, like, 20, 25% of their income.
Only half as much as the rest of the population.
We didn't know that 5 years ago.
Now that's established fact.
So that's the first kind of novelty.
And the book is really about that, is about first,
telling people about this new
international research effort and what we've
learned from that.
And then it comes,
in addition, to answer your question, to kind of
the gigantic increase in wealth inequality.
And especially in the wealth of the super-rich,
including
the UK.
Let me just mention the numbers.
Yeah, go ahead.
For the UK because
I don't think
that people necessarily have that well in mind.
If you look at the Sunday Times,
Rich list.
It exists since 1989.
1989 the top 0.001% of the wealth distribution,
so that's roughly the 200 wealthiest families,
they owned, in wealth, the equivalent of 5%
of the UK's GDP.
Yeah.
Meaning, if they spent all their wealth, they could buy,
they could have bought the equivalent of 5%
of all the goods and services
produced in a given year in the entire country.
Okay?
Recently, they just released their latest numbers,
their latest ranking, and now that same group
of the population owns the equivalent of 25% of GDP,
in wealth, meaning,
you have 200 families,
if they spent all their wealth, they could buy a quarter
of everything that's produced in a given year
in this country
You're convinced inequality is,
is increasing aggressively?
Well, when you look at those numbers,
it's
pretty, difficult to claim that it's,
it's not rising.
But then, you know, people sometimes argue,
"No, inequality is not increasing a lot"
because they look at other parts of the population.
If you look at the top
10% as a whole,
but here we're talking about the super-rich.
We're talking about billionaires.
The real problem is that top, the very, very top end.
I'm not saying it's the only problem,
but it's where
the trend has been the most powerful,
the most spectacular,
and also the most worrying for demo- for
democracies.
Because you might say, "Okay, these...
Who cares about these 200 people?"
Well, you know, you look at the media they own.
Yeah.
You look at their influence on politics and policies.
Look, wealth for most people
is, it's a good thing, right?
For the middle class,
it's owning a home.
It's pensions for your old days.
It's safety
in case shocks happen.
You lose your job.
It's great.
We like to encourage wealth accumulation
by the middle class.
For the working class,
they don't have access to property.
Not yet.
The working class, the bottom 50%
of the distribution almost owns no wealth.
Their debts are about as high as their assets.
We like to encourage access...
We'd like the working class
to have access to wealth.
So we want to encourage wealth accumulation in general.
Now, for the super-rich, wealth is not,
not accumulating billions
for their old days, right?
For them, wealth is power.
Yeah.
It's the power to influence the prevailing ideology.
It's the power to influence markets by buying
competitors.
It's the power to influence politics
by buying elections, by influencing policymaking,
and there is always,
a fundamental tension in democratic societies
between the concentration of wealth on the one hand and
extreme wealth in particular,
and the very possibility of a democratic society.
All the people who have
written on democracy back to Aristotle,
they've written about that.
So you think democracy is in threat.
You think if we don't tax
the very, very rich, this small group of society
will amass more and more and more wealth and power,
and
it will take wealth and power away from ordinary people.
That's, but that's exactly what's happening, right?
Yeah.
It's this kind of loop where
wealth begets power, which begets more wealth.
Yes.
And look at what's happening,
in the US with
frankly the plutocratic collapse.
And you think that...
Yeah.
Just yesterday,
like, the... the government announced
that Trump had signed a deal with the IRS,
according to which he and his family
would be shielded from any tax audit
for the rest of their life.
Okay.
Because Trump, had sued the IRS
because his tax return had been disclosed,
and he was asking $10 billion from
the agency that he controls as president.
And they settled on, okay, let's make a deal.
You're not going to have to pay me 10 billion.
Yeah.
But from now on, you're forbidden from just auditing
my tax returns or those of my children.
Look,
the degree,
not only of corruption, but the total,
oligarchy capture of the government.
And you have to also realise how fast it can happen.
Yeah.
Because sometimes people look at the US and
they're like, "You know, whatever happens there cannot
happen here." But no, no, first, it's a global trend.
It can happen very fast.
I've experienced it firsthand in France.
The 2% minimum tax proposal.
Like, you know, minimalistic.
Everybody should be in favour.
86% of the population is in favour.
And the billionaires, when it came very close
to passing a few month ago, they used all the media
that they own, and they own 85% of the private press.
They own all the economic newspapers
of the country except one.
And they used it to stoke fears
and to predict all sorts of catastrophes,
and more importantly, to essentially threaten,
elected representatives, to blackmail them,
essentially saying, "Look, if you vote for that..."
They didn't say that as explicitly,
but that was really the substance of the message.
"If you vote for that bill,
for that proposal, we will fight you
with all our weapons and all our money."
I'm going to have to push you
for some quick answers on the UK political situation,
because I know we're short of time.
Here in the UK, there is a very real possibility
that we will get a new prime minister,
maybe as soon as in the next couple of months.
But,
if not, quite possibly in the next year and a half.
A new prime minister's going to come in.
The current government is very unpopular.
The new prime minister will have to have an is-
an answer on what they're going to do with the economy.
We have been pushing very hard for a number of years
now that we think the UK government should
be more serious about the taxation of the super-rich.
It should.
If the new prime minister was willing
to do something more serious on the top end,
is it practically possible, and would you be willing
to support the new prime minister
in designing and implementing those taxes
such that they work for the UK economy?
Yes, and yes, 100%.
So is it practical?
A lot of the work that we've done over the last
few years has been to study the historical experience
with wealth taxation in many countries,
like France, Germany used to have wealth taxes,
and abolished in many cases their wealth taxes.
And what's important to understand is that
those wealth taxes, they really didn't work very well.
Okay.
That is true, and that's often an argument
that you hear from opponents of wealth taxation.
They said, "Oh, it's been tried in the past
and it failed." I agree with that part of the statement.
That's correct.
They were really poorly done.
But there are 2 ways to look at that experience.
You can say, "Well, we've tried in the past.
It didn't work, hence it will never work, end of story.
We can't do anything.
We have to accept that the
super-rich live in their own parallel society, tax-free.
There's not much that we can do."
It's one way to look at it.
The other way is to say,
"Okay, let's try to learn about history.
Let's try to learn about the mistakes that were made,
and draw lessons and see if there are solutions."
And there are solutions.
And so the two key ingredients
you need to make a tax based on wealth for the
super-rich work well in practice are the following.
Number one, you need to make sure that
there is no way to avoid the tax, and tax avoidance,
it's not a law of nature, it's manmade.
It's when lawmakers introduce in the law exemptions
or deductions.
And all the wealth taxes that existed in Europe,
they were written in that way.
Like France, it's totally crazy.
It's a story I tell in the book.
In France, the Socialist Party,
the Socialist Party comes into power in 1981.
They create a wealth tax,
and then immediately they change it
to exempt the billionaires from the wealth tax.
And of course, they don't go on TV
and say, "Look, we're going to exempt the billionaires."
And also, they invent a little story.
They say that it's very important
to protect business assets from the wealth
tax, because otherwise, we are going to harm businesses.
And they define professional assets.
That's how they call it,
and they define professional assets,
that exists nowhere in any economics textbook,
so they invent this notion,
and they define professional assets
as owning more than 25% of the shares of a company.
So if you're really rich,
you own a lot of shares in a big business,
then all of that was exempted from the wealth tax.
That's what they put in the law, right?
But it's totally crazy.
It's like if the US was creating a wealth tax
today and was exempting Elon Musk or Jeff Bezos
from the wealth tax.
That's what the French Socialists did in 1981.
But importantly, everybody understands that
we can write the law differently, right?
So the idea behind the proposal
is let's start really high in the wealth distribution.
So only people who have more than £100 million
will be affected by the tax.
But in exchange for this very high threshold,
no exemption, no deduction whatsoever.
Everybody understands that
if you at... you are at that level of wealth,
and we're talking about 1,000 families roughly in the UK,
that you have a high ability to pay taxes,
and so you don't need any kind of exemption whatsoever.
Now, if you write things like that,
it's already a huge progress
relative to the past wealth taxes.
So that's number one.
The second crucial ingredient
is how do you deal with the threat of migration?
Rich people, always the debate boils down to,
"Okay, perhaps it would be good to tax the super-rich,
but they're going to move.
They're going to move to Dubai,
to Monaco, and we can't do anything." This is wrong.
Okay.
It's wrong that...
It's not wrong that they will move.
Surely some of them will.
Those flows tend to be exaggerated
in the public debate, but it's not 0.
But what is wrong is this idea
that we are powerless to curb
this tax exile.
We are not powerless because any country on its own,
let's take the UK, could say the following.
It could say,
"Look, if someone has lived for a long time in the UK,
number one, and number two,
has become extremely rich in the UK,
and now, number three, moves to another country,
that's their right.
Fine.
But we, the UK, we will keep taxing that person
as if he or she was still a resident of the UK
for 5 years or 10 years.
We can discuss." Okay?
And any country on its own
can do that so that there would be no incentive anymore
for the super-rich to move for tax reasons.
And so then you might say, "Well, it's impossible.
It's never been done."
Well, no, that's what the US does.
The US is even more extreme than that.
The US says, "If you has...
If you have US citizenship
and you move to another country,
you have to pay taxes to the US until you die."
Yeah.
That's somewhat extreme, right?
Because, okay, imagine someone who was born in the US,
has US citizenship, their parents moved
when they were two months old, then...
And then the person never sets foot again in the US.
In principle,
that person has to pay taxes in the US until she dies.
Well, that's somewhat extreme.
But what the UK and what all other countries do is
the opposite extreme, because what we do at the moment is
we let people who have spent all their life in the UK,
who have become immensely rich in the UK, we let them go
tax-free as soon as they move, as soon as they leave.
You know, on January 1st.
It's totally crazy.
And it's not, it's not essential.
We don't have to do that.
And we don't have to do that.
Yeah.
We could say,
"Okay, look, you want to go to Dubai, go to Dubai.
But from a tax perspective,
you will still be treated as a resident of the UK
for 10 years,
let's say."
Quick one last one.
So while you're here, I really want to get you...
I really want to get the political classes in the UK
to see you and hear you because
the argument for the wealth tax and wealth taxes here
in the UK is very loud, very popular with the public.
But many of the political classes
view it as unrealistic.
And The Rest is Politics,
which is the biggest politics podcast in this country,
Rory Stewart, one of the presenters,
said that, pushed back on the idea that there is any...
He said there is no academic consensus.
He said, "Where are the academics?
Where are the people with post-graduate degrees?
Where are the professors?"
So what do you say to Rory Stewart,
the presenter of the biggest politics podcast
in the country,
about the idea that no academics support this,
and would you be willing to go on The Rest is Politics
and show them that there are academics who support this?
Yeah.
I say to Rory Stewart that he should,
read a bit more and listen a bit more
to what's happening in the rest of the world,
and he would realise very quickly that there is,
in fact,
overwhelming support, even among academic economists,
of course, in the general population,
but more importantly for your question,
among economists for this proposal.
Like, for instance, in July of 2025,
there was an op-ed in Le Monde
that was signed by 7 Nobel Prize winners.
7 Nobel winners.
7 Nobel Prize winners
who wrote
"We support this pr..." It was exactly
about this proposal.
And 2% minimum tax on the super-rich,
2% of their wealth,
and they supported France doing it on its own.
Don't wait for an international agreement.
Lead by example.
Do it.
And, you know, they explain the logic,
the failure of our tax system today
to effectively tax the super-rich,
why that's the right approach to fixing that problem.
7 Nobel Prize winners.
You know, Joe Stiglitz, Paul
Krugman, Esther Duflo, Daron Acemoglu, and many others.
Then in the debate in France,
you had other economists, many economists
who came out strongly in support.
Like, for instance, the former chief economist
of the IMF, Olivier Blanchard.
We wrote an op-ed together in Le Monde saying...
And he said, "That's the right proposal.
Do it." He's not a left-wing person.
He's not a communist.
And,
so, broadly speaking, you have about 80%,
90% of the population which is in favour,
and you have broadly the same proportion
among economists.
You always have 10, 20% of the population
who thinks that,
It's normal for some people to be above the law
That the super-rich,
they are so kind of smart and so good
Yeah
that it's a kind of natural aristocracy,
and that we have to accept
that they pay less tax than the rest of us.
And in any case, there's nothing we can do about
fixing that and that the law should be more lenient
on the powerful and harsher on the poor
and immigrants.
But it's always a small fraction of the population.
Most of the population everywhere wants equality
before the law.
And that's true for people just like for economists.
And fundamentally, this taxation of the wealth
of the extremely wealthy, it's about that.
It's about this fundamental principle
that you cannot have...
You cannot live in your,
in your own separate society.
You have to abide by our fundamental principle
of equality before the law.
You have to pay at least as much as nurses
and school teachers.
And it's just not acceptable
you should be able to pay 0.
And you would be willing to go on The Rest is Politics
and explain that to them?
Of course.
I fought it.
Because, you know, I'd love for you to go on there.
And I really think this is
the big economic issue of our time,
and I think any serious political podcast,
you know, you are the world leader on this,
I think they should be speaking to you.
I can see we're out of time.
Have you got one final message to the British public,
and the Australians,
and Americans, and New Zealanders who might be watching?
Yeah, now's the time, frankly.
We are the beginning of an international movement
where you have this proposal,
these questions
that are discussed in different countries.
We need one country to lead by example,
to step ahead and say, "You know what?
We have public finance problems.
We have investment needs.
We need to invest in education,
in healthcare, in our public infrastructure"
which is at the core of our collective prosperity.
And we are going to do that first
by taxing the super-rich.
It's not going to be enough, but it's necessary.
And you know what, what's going to happen
if one country does that?
It will demonstrate that you can get a lot of revenue.
For the UK,
we're talking about £15 billion per year
from just taxing at 2% the wealth of the super-rich.
And the sun is going to keep rising in the morning.
Okay?
And then once one country does it, many count- ma-
many countries very fast will start doing it,
and that's how you create this international movement.
Okay.
So you,
It could be us
I count on you.
It could be in the UK.
It can be.
When often, the UK has led.
The UK was
one of the first countries
to create a progressive income tax, 1909.
The UK was the first country
to create the welfare state in 1945.
So now's the time to lead again.
Okay.
Well, I hope it is.
So thank you very much for your time.
Gabriel's new book,
We Need to Tax Billionaires, is just out now.
It's very short and it's very easy to read.
I read it on one flight.
Like, this is just giving you all the details,
basically of how to do it,
and the details of how to do it.
And I've been following Gabriel's work for years.
He's been helping me for years.
I'm really excited about getting this book
and Gabriel in front of the UK political class because,
you know, we can do it, and it's not just,
crazy YouTubers like me.
It is also prestigious academics.
So thank you very much, and this is Gabriel Zucman.
Hey.
Thank
You very much for coming.
My pleasure.
Thank you for all your help over the years.
Good luck with your work.
Good luck to you, too.